Evelyn Shrifte Collection Relating to Vanguard Press
Evelyn Shrifte Collection Relating to Vanguard Press
1928-1990
Shrifte, Evelyn.
3 linear ft.
Correspondence and memorabilia relating to Vanguard Press, of which Shrifte was president for more than thirty-five years. Includes correspondence with several notable authors including Saul Bellow, Pierre Boulle, Joyce Carol Oates, and Madeleine L'Engle.
2989494
Biographical History
The Vanguard Press was established in 1926 with a $100,000 grant from the Garland Fund, a philanthropic foundation. The Garland Fund was noted for its support of left-wing and radical causes, organizations and institutions, and Vanguard Press published a wide assortment of new and classic works on radical topics, including studies of the Soviet Union, socialist theory, and politically-oriented fiction. In 1932 the press severed its relationship with the Garland Fund and moved into publishing more mainstream authors and titles. The firm was sold to a larger publishing firm in the late 1930s and in 1988 it was acquired by Random House.
Evelyn Shrifte (1900 or 1901-1999) was an American editor and president of Vanguard Publishing for more than thirty-five years. Educated at Barnard College, she worked for the Musical Quarterly and owned and operated a bookstore in New York City before going to work for Vanguard in the early 1930s. She became its president in 1952, a position she held until Vanguard's sale to Random House in 1988. Among the books published during her tenure were Saul Bellow's first two novels, Dr. Seuss' first two books, and many novels by Joyce Carol Oates.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1928 to 1990, the Evelyn Shrifte Collection Relating to Vanguard Press comprises correspondence and memorabilia relating to Vanguard Press, of which Shrifte served as president from 1952 to 1988, when it was sold to Random House. Although the bulk of the Vanguard Press Archive was subsequently donated to Columbia University Library, Evelyn Shrifte retained an assortment of materials relating to a number of authors with whom she had worked.
Correspondence-subject files (Boxes 1-4) contains any combination of incoming and outgoing personal and business letters, book manuscripts, and printed material pertaining to Vanguard Press authors Saul Bellow, James T. Farrell, Theodor Geisel (Dr. Seuss), Joyce Carol Oates, Robert Phillips, and Edith Sitwell, among others. Of greatest depth and duration (1948-1962) are materials relating to a number of Sitwell titles, including The Canticle of the Rose, Collected Poems, English Eccentrics, and Music and Ceremonies. In addition, the collection includes two versions of the Dr. Seuss manuscript for The 500 Hats of Bartholomew Cubbins.
A history of Vanguard Press, notes for two projects, five catalogs from between the years 1928 and 1938, and an assortment of reviews constitute Memorabilia.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically.
Separated Material
Three story manuscripts ("Did You Ever Slip on Red Blood?"; "The Lady with Pet Dog"; "Nightmusic") and the partial manuscript for an unpublished novel, How Lucien Florey Died, and Was Born, have been transferred to and integrated with the
Joyce Carol Oates Papers
. Two published books by Louis Slobodkin have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging; please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Publishing, printing and book arts; Boulle, Pierre, 1912-1994.; L'Engle, Madeleine.; Oates, Joyce Carol, 1938-; Seuss, Dr.; Shrifte, Evelyn.; Sitwell, Edith, 1887-1964.; Slobodkin, Louis, 1903-1975.; Vanguard Press.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Artwork.; Book reviews.; Catalogs (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Publishers and publishing.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bernice Woll, 1999.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Aistrop, Jack Bentley, 1965; 1968 (Box 1)
  - Allan, Mabel Esther, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Bader, Barbara, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Banning, Evelyn I., 1964 (Box 1)
  - Beach, Edward Latimer, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Beaton-Jones, Cynon, 1968; 1989 (Box 1)
  - Bellow, Saul, 1944-1948; 1964,; undated; photocopies of correspondence with James Henle and Evelyn Shrifte (Box 1)
  - Benasutti, Marion, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Blackwell, Louise, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Boulle, Pierre, 1989; 1992,; undated (Box 1)
  - Brandon, Evan, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Carter, Helene, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Cavanah, Frances, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chapelle, Howard Irving, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Cheesebrough, Sue, undated (Box 1)
  - Closs, August, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Conrad, Sybil, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Cooper, Brian, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Corsaro, Frank, undated; Falstaff drawing (watercolor and crayon) (Oversize 1)
  - Cost, March, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Ethridge, Willie Snow [1968], 1978 (Box 1)
  - Fabricant, Noah D., 1958 (Box 1)
  - Farrell, James T., 1954-1957; 1976
    - The Face of Time, partial manuscript, various paging; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - The University of Kansas City Review (inscribed issue, Summer 1945 (Box 1)
    - Transcripts of letters from Evelyn Shrifte, 1953-1956 (Box 1)
  - Fisher, Avery, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Franklin, Hugh, See L'Engle, Madeleine.
  - Frenaye, Frances, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Gallenkamp, Charles, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Gardner, Diana, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Garnett, Richard, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Geisel, Theodor Seuss, See Seuss, Dr..
  - Gillon, Philip, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Gottlieb, Robert, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Hannum, Alberta, 1970; undated (Box 1)
  - Heard, Gerald, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Helwig, Hans, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Heyen, William, 1976; 1989 (Box 1)
  - Hogeboom, Amy, undated (Box 1)
  - Ianovskii, Vasilii S., 1980 (Box 1)
  - Jagendorf, Moritz Adolph, 1959; 1962,; undated (Box 1)
  - Jenkyns, Chris, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Jones, Bruce E., 1989 (Box 1)
  - Kasdan, Sara, 1956-1957; 1965 (Box 1)
  - Kling, Samuel G., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Knopf, Alfred A., 1926 (Box 1)
  - Knopf, Blanche, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Leekley, Thomas B., 1959 (Box 1)
  - L'Engle, Madeleine, 1964; 1983 (Box 1)
  - Long, Barbara, undated (Box 1)
  - Marion, John Francis, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Marsh, Gwen, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Mayfield, Julian, 1970 (Box 1)
  - McCann's, 1947 (Box 1)
  - McGinnis, Bruce, 1989 (Box 1)
  - McKenna, Rollie, 1955 (Box 1)
  - McKone, Jim, 1990 (Box 1)
  - McKown, Robin, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Mizener, Arthur, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Morrison, Margaret Mackie, See Cost, March.
  - Nourse, James I., 1968 (Box 1)
  - Oates, Joyce Carol, 1969; 1972-1974,; 1986 (Box 2)
  - Philipson, Morris H., 1968 (Box 2)
  - Phillips, Robert
    - General, 1967; 1968,; 1970,; 1990 (Box 2)
    - Face to Face (Houston: Wing Press) (inscribed copy), 1993 (Box 2)
    - Inner Weather (Francestown, N.H.: Golden Quill Press, circa 1966) (Box 2)
    - The Pregnant Man (Garden City: Doubleday) (inscribed copy), 1978 (Box 2)
  - Potok, Chaim, 1982 (photocopy) (Box 2)
  - Ross, Bill D., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Rudge, William Edwin, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Ruhm, Herbert, 1962; 1989 (Box 2)
  - Russell, Robert, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Salter, Stefan, See Wolf, Helen.
  - Self, Margaret Cabell, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Seuss, Dr.
    - The 500 Hats of Bartholomew Cubbins, manuscript, with pencil corrections and annotations, 2 versions (Box 2)
  - Sitwell, Edith
    - General, 1948-1962; undated (Box 2)
    - The Canticle of the Rose
      - Correspondence (telegrams), 1949 (Box 2)
      - Galley proofs, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - "Proof of finished plate", 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Page proofs (Box 3)
      - Selected pages, with corrections (New York: Vanguard, c1940) (inscribed) (Box 3)
    - Collected Poems
      - Section 1949-1954, editing questions (Box 3)
    - English Eccentrics
      - Typescript manuscripts (partial) (Box 3)
      - Production records (partial) (Box 3)
    - Music and Ceremonies
      - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 3)
      - Production records, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - "The Wind of Early Spring", holograph poem "For Evelyn Shrifte" (Box 3)
  - Slade, Caroline, 1959; undated (Box 3)
  - Slobodkin, Florence and Louis
    - Sarah Somebody (New York: Vanguard Press, circa 1969), photocopy, with notes (Box 3)
  - Slobodkin, Louis
    - Hustle and Bustle (New York: Macmillan), 1948; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - One Is Good, But Two Are Better, artwork and production records (Oversize 1)
    - Our Friendly Friends (New York: Vanguard), circa 1951; Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
  - Sootin, Harry, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Tabor, Grace, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Trease, Geoffrey, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Venezis, Ilias, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Waller, George Macgregor, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Weart, Edith Lucie, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Weaver, Harriett E., 1988; 1989 (Box 4)
  - Wier, Ester, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Willingham, Calder, 1968; 1976; includes 18-page enclosure to H. Wouk (Box 4)
  - Wiseman, Ann Sayre, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Wolf, Patricia, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Wolff, Helen, 1982 appeal on behalf of book designer Stefan Salter, also two copies of manuscript ("Balance Sheet") by Salter (Box 4)
  - Woytinsky, Wladimir S., 1989 (Box 4)
  - Yanovsky, V. S., See Ianovskii, Vasilii S..
  - Zaidenberg, Arthur, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Rights and permissions, 1957-1988 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1990; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Days with Lenin, International Publishers, 1932 (Box 4)
  - History of Vanguard Press, circa 1980; typescript manuscript by unknown author (Box 4)
  - Masterpieces of Hogarth, Frederick A. Stokes Co., undated (Box 4)
  - Notes (2) about possible projects, undated (Box 4)
  - P.M.: an Intimate Journal for Production Managers, Art Directors, and Their Associates, Feb-May 1936 (Box 4)
  - Publicity (Box 4)
    - Catalogs, 1928; 1930,; 1933,; 1935,; 1938 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Reviews of Vanguard Press authors (Box 4)